- Bert Spencer:
Give me a minute.
If it's fucking important
to me--and this is going
to start the program.
- Producer: Yes.
- Bert Spencer: Yes?
- Bert Spencer:
Alright, you bastards.
You're not
beneath--Christ.
Tell me when.
My name is Bert Spencer.
I don't run, and I don't hide,
and I to tend to say it
as it is, regardless.
Many of you will remember
my name in relation
to the murder
of Carl Bridgewater.
I did not kill Carl Bridgewater,
and I am here to prove
to you that I did not.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
On the 19 of September 1978,
13-year-old Carl Bridgewater
left his home in Woodley
in the West Midlands.
Like thousands of other
children across the country,
he was carrying
out a paper route.
- Carl's Father:
He's a reliable lad.
You know you could always rely
on him to do things, you know,
never had no worries about
him doing a newspaper route.
- James D'Arcy: At 4 PM, Karl,
was making one of his final
deliveries of the
day to Yew Tree farm.
The occupants, an
elderly couple, were out.
- "Hello?"
- James D'Arcy: It seems Carl
entered the farmhouse and
disturbed a burglary.
Carl was then shot at
point-blank face with a shotgun.
The cold-blooded murder sparked
one of the biggest police
manhunts for a child
killer ever seen in the UK.
- Bob Stewart: We have
a good witness and a very
clear and lucid
type of witness,
and he had a
very good close look at a man
sitting behind the wheel
of what is probably
a blue estate car.
There is a distinct possibility
that this is one of the men
that we are looking for.
- James D'Arcy: The police's
suspicions were quickly aroused
by a local ambulance
officer, Bert Spencer.
- Bert Spencer's Daughter: They
told me, that the paperboy,
Carl, has been shot.
And I just sat there, and
I thought, "Oh my God, "
and my dad was
number one suspect.
- James D'Arcy: But just as
it looked like Bert Spencer
could've been arrested and
charged with the crime,
events took
an unexpected turn.
Detectives picked up a gang
of robbers for a burglary at
a nearby farm, known as
the Bridgewater Four,
they were convicted and
imprisoned for Carl's murder,
but almost immediately,
rumors circulated that
the men had been
figured out by a corrupt
police force eager
to solve the crime.
A rumor that was proven to
be true when after 20 years,
the men's conviction
was squashed,
and they were free to go.
With Carl's killer
still at large,
the crime remains one of
the UK's most notorious,
unsolved murders.
- The one who pulled
the trigger and I wish
I could
get my hands on him.
It's very hard to describe
the feelings to a person.
- James D'Arcy: Although Bert
Spencer was never charged
with Carl's murder,
he has lived under the constant
shadow of suspicion.
Now, he has decided
it's time to speak out.
♪ music playing ♪
- News Reporter: The murder of 13-year-old Carl Bridgewater,
even by the grizzly
standards of murder itself at
Yew Tree Farm in Staffordshire,
on the afternoon of September
1978 was a boy on his after
school newspaper round,
he unknowingly disturbed an
antique's burglary at this
lonely farm house, and
was brutally shot down.
- Carl's Father: It was evening
meal time, like you know,
and we usually sat down to
our evening meal all together,
and Carl hadn't returned,
and Janet got a bit worried,
you see...so I went
to look for him.
When I got down
by Yew Tree Farm,
there was a police
car there, you see,
so I pulled up and asked him
if he had seen a paperboy.
I told him, you know,
and that's when he said there
had been an incident
with a boy, you know,
and I had to wait.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy: West Midlands police reconstructed
Carl's last known
movements in a bid to job
the public's memory
and maybe find an eye-witness
or other clues.
- Bob Stewart: I am quite
sure that the offenders went
to the farm house
to break in and steal
antiques and as I said,
I'm looking for a link,
you know,
of similar offenses.
- James D'Arcy: As police began
to gather witness statements,
there was one in
particular that stood out.
Local company director Roger
Edwards gave a very specific
account of a vehicle
and its driver.
- Roger Edwards: I saw
a pale blue saloon car,
a Vauxhall Viva, turning
into Yew Tree Farm.
I noticed
the driver was a man.
He was wearing a
dark blue uniform.
- James D'Arcy: The police
searched records for all
owners of such a vehicle
in a 50-mile radius.
The only one who wore
a uniform at work was
ambulance officer
Bert Spencer.
Once the police realized that
Bert was also a part-time
antiques dealer, he became
a focus of their inquiries.
This is an excerpt of the police
interview with Bert in his
kitchen, just days after
the murder of Carl.
- Bert Spencer:
"I'm a married man,
residing with my wife and
family at the above address.
I'm very interested in
antiques, mainly clocks.
On occasion, I purchase
things for my collection.
I'm not a dealer.
I'm employed by the West
Midlands Health Authority.
On Tuesday, 19 of September,
I was on duty at the hospital
from approximately 8:30
until approximately 5:10.
I'm the registered owner of a
Vauxhall Viva saloon motorcar."
- James D'Arcy: In that
first police interview,
there was some vital
information which Bert chose
not to tell the police.
Most importantly, that he
had been a neighbor of the
Bridgewater's for several
years and had regularly hunted
with a shotgun on land
surrounding Yew Tree Farm.
- Simon Golding: "Hello,
professor Wilson,
my name is Simon Golding.
I'm a journalist and writer,
and have been working on a
book--a biography of sorts,
the man called Bert Spencer.
I was wondering if
you would be interested
in possibly
interviewing Bert.
Anyway, thank you for
your time and I look forward
to hearing from you.
Bye now."
- David Wilson:
"Hi, Simon.
Thanks for your message.
It's professor David
Wilson here, I absolutely
do know of--that Spencer is--
- James D'Arcy:
Criminologist David Wilson
is used by police forces
across the country
to get inside the
minds of murderers.
- David Wilson: The murder
of Carl Bridgewater is one
of the most infamous,
unsolved murders in
British criminal
history and if Bert Spencer
has agreed
to be interviewed,
that's too good of an
opportunity to miss.
- Bert Spencer: Yes,
I did speak to Simon,
and he said
someone might ring.
I won't tolerate liars.
I have never been and
there's no need of it.
Whatever you have
heard about the case,
you've heard
and nothing yet.
- David Wilson: Well, having
read about him for four weeks
is at least good to
finally see him.
Quite the extraordinary garden
and he's giving me a wave.
That's very kind of him.
Coming out to
meet me, as well.
Chatting away.
This garden is
quite extraordinary.
Well, I've read
so much about you,
it's a
pleasure to meet you.
I am.
It's very
nice to meet you.
How are you?
- Bert Spencer: Alright, mate.
I'm so pleased to meet you.
- David Wilson: Well,
it's lovely to meet you.
Thank you for asking us.
- Bert Spencer: I've heard
a lot of it about you,
some of it was good.
You're more than welcome
to come in to our home.
- David Wilson: Thank you.
- Christine Spencer:
Hello, I'm Christine.
- David Wilson: Christine,
hello, my name is David Wilson.
It's very nice to meet you.
- Christine Wilson: I've heard
quite a lot about you.
- David Wilson: Oh, well
I hope some of it was
as good as he promised.
- Bert Spencer: Some
of it, come on in.
- David Wilson: And what
are all the decorations?
I s this your hobby,
your interest?
- Bert Spencer: Well,
I love my garden.
I only have a small garden,
but I do love gardening.
Just make it look a
bit tidy, that's all.
Come on.
- David Wilson: Thank you.
- Bert Spencer: Just
go on in and relax.
You're welcome, go on
in, just go on in there.
- David Wilson: Bert,
are these your paintings?
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
Some of them are in here.
Some got burnt when my former
wife had a funny and threw
me out, and she burnt
a lot in the garden.
Lots of things she burnt, but
these are some of them, yes.
Yeah.
- David Wilson: She
burnt your paintings?
- Bert Spencer:
Burnt a lot of stuff.
- David Wilson: Why
would she do that?
- Bert Spencer: Well, she
went a little bit unwell.
And she used to
that now and again,
and that's one of
those episodes.
Yeah, burnt a lot of stuff.
I was at work at the time.
- David Wilson: Also,
you're an ambulance officer.
- Bert Spencer: Oh, that's
from a long time ago, yeah.
I did 19 years with them.
The problem is, anything
good you've done in life like
saving lives, delivering
babies, that was lovely.
Helping deliver babies,
that was beautiful.
It doesn't count for
anything when you get
yourself in to trouble.
It's all demolished.
And it's a shame.
really, because it's
still in my mind.
It's still in my heart.
I'm still in my heart
an ambulance man,
although physically
I can't be now.
- David Wilson: How do
you define yourself then?
- Bert Spencer:
Just a pensioner.
- David Wilson:
Just as a pensioner?
- Bert Spencer: With no value.
I'll--I'll qualify
that later on.
I have no value no society.
Okay, that's what I--that's how
I define myself, but I'm happy.
I'm alive.
I wake up every day and
say, "I'm alive, thank you,
whoever you are."
- David Wilson:
Well, how about a cup of tea
and then maybe
start formally having a chat.
- Bert Spencer: You
want a cup of tea?
That's 30 pens.
- David Wilson: I'm
sure I've got it.
I'm sure I've got a 30 p.
- Bert Spencer: Come with me.
- David Wilson: Thank you.
- Bert Spencer:
Now, throughout this day--
- David Wilson:
The first thing that
I know about
you is that you were born
in December 1939.
- Bert Spencer:
In the war years.
- David Wilson: In the war year,
and I just wanted to know
about the family background
that you were born into.
- Bert Spencer: I
started the war.
I rang it, lad.
I said, "Hey you bastard, you
bombed out our tip shot."
- David Wilson: Can you
describe for me, Bert,
the relationship that you had
with your mother and father?
Who were you closest to?
- Bert Spencer: My dad
was a sort of block,
he was allegedly
a hard bastard.
Okay?
I don't hold
a lot against him.
- David Wilson:
What did he do?
- Bert Spencer: He used to go
around collecting scrap
iron on the horse and trap.
And in those days,
in the market towns,
in the market you'd
have a boxing ring,
and they'd have some sort
of bruiser there, drunk.
And you could go in and if you
could face two round with him,
you'd get a wide 5 pound note.
And my dad used to go in
to get his beer money.
- David Wilson: Your mother
and your father separated?
- Bert Spencer: They separated.
I don't know how old
I was--I really don't.
My mother and my sister
and my elders wouldn't
let us talk about
him because we had a granny
sitting in the armchair there, in the Windsor chair.
She was in charge of
the house in those days.
The granny was in charge, and
you didn't answer granny back,
or else you got a cloud.
Yeah.
I don't remember a great deal,
except I did love my horse--his
horse and I loved my dad, but
I wasn't allowed to go to him.
He had to come and steal
me when I was playing.
Mother worked in
a factory, crikey,
God knows how many hours, and we
had a tiny house in Smethwick,
no lights, no fire,
no coal, no money,
and I was put into
Dr. Menardo's home.
- David Wilson:
What was that like?
- Bert Spencer: I was beaten
a bloody savage in there.
We were in a dormitory,
then one day,
I woke up and my
bed was ringing wet.
I never, ever wet the
bed and I don't today.
Went down to one
of the breakfast was,
and we all had to line
up, there were nuns there.
Nuns.
And we all had to grab a great
big spoon of cod liver oil.
"You got to have it.
Next."
And I was called
to some office, somewhere,
and I was caned,
bloody Christ.
- David Wilson:
What age were you?
- Bert Spencer: Maybe 9--10.
My hands were on fire, and they
marched me to a big kitchen
thing, with a great big bell
fast sink and my sheets were
in there with hot water.
"Wash those sheets,"
and I kept saying,
"It wasn't me.
I didn't wet the bed."
"How dare you lie?
How dare you lie?"
- David Wilson: Bert, how
did the sheets get wet?
- Bert Spencer: Well,
I know now--I know now,
there were some
bullies in there.
I don't tolerate bullies.
One of them peed the
bed, he was in the gang,
and when we went
out of the room,
he tooled my mattress and
put his mattress and sheets.
And I got--God, the
fire in my hands!
And while that was
on, I was screaming,
and I had to go in this
hot water and wash sheets.
- James D'Arcy: With
no formal education,
Bert was forced into a
series of low paid jobs.
His life looked like it was
about to drift into petty crime
and a pattern was
beginning to emerge,
but freedom from his harsh
beginnings came following a
chance encounter with an
ambulance driver at a local pub,
which saw Bert sign
up to the service.
For the first time, Bert
felt a sense of belonging,
and relishing the
newfound responsibility,
he would rise rapidly
through the ranks.
From ambulance driver to
ambulance liaison officer.
- David Wilson: What was it
that appealed to you
about ambulance driving?
That's been
a recurring theme.
- Bert Spencer: I
know, I don't know.
- David Wilson:
What did you like?
The responsibility?
- Bert Spencer: We used to go
out in the middle of the night,
helping babies.
We used to stop in the snow
and mom would have a baby.
So, I took a course to make sure
I'd never do anything wrong.
The baby would survive my
rough handling as it were.
Time and time again, in
the middle of the night,
in the snow and the baby would
come along and I'd--I did
whatever I could, and eventually
we'd get to a hospital,
and these little
things, soaking wet,
covered in blood and this
tiny thing, I got life.
And I don't know what it is.
I'm getting emotional.
- David Wilson: I know you are.
You-- - Bert Spencer:
Can we just wait a bit?
- David Wilson: Yes, yes.
Of course!
You tell me when you
feel ready to start.
- Bert Spencer: Come on.
- David Wilson: It's fine, we're
going through emotional stuff.
- I have come here
to stop this lie.
I had no involvement in
the Carl Bridgewater murder,
I did not kill Carl.
No involvement whatsoever.
- James D'Arcy: Since 1978,
the murder of Carl Bridgewater
has cast a long shadow
across Bert's life.
His determination to clear
his name once and for all,
has been the driving force
behind allowing David Wilson
to interview him now.
- David Wilson: Let's talk about
the death of Carl Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: Where were
you when you first heard
the news that Carl Bridgewater
had been murdered?
- Bert Spencer: At home.
No, sorry, sorry!
I was at
work the next day.
- David Wilson:
How did you react?
- Bert Spencer: Bloody hell!
- David Wilson: When you
were first interviewed--
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: By the police,
here was this shocking
murder of a paperboy.
You knew the farm.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: You
knew the family.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson:
The Bridgewater's,
but you didn't really offer
very much to the police
in that first interview.
- Bert Spencer: I knew them.
They weren't
personal friends.
I know you.
You're not
a personal friend.
So, if you got stabbed
tomorrow in Boston,
I don't have much to offer.
I knew you, yes.
- David Wilson: There is
a witness who says that
he saw a Vauxhall Viva.
- Bert Spencer: Right.
- David Wilson: Which
you had at the time.
- Bert Spencer: Right.
- David Wilson: And the person
driving the Vauxhall Viva
was wearing a uniform
with two pips on it.
- Bert Spencer: Thank
you for saying that.
If you went down to Yew
Tree Farm, down the lane,
and saw a Vauxhall
Viva turning left,
you'd see the back of a
Vauxhall Viva turning left,
you'd think nothing
else whatsoever.
You just mentioned a car that
could have been mine, it wasn't.
- James D'Arcy: In order
to check Bert's statement,
police visited his workplace,
Colbert Hospital in Woodsley.
They were particularly
interested in the alibi,
which his secretary,
Barbara, provided.
- Barbara: "I can confirm
that Mr. Hubert Spencer was
at Colbert Hospital
all afternoon."
- James D'Arcy:
What Bert didn't tell the police
was that he and
Barbara were close friends
and neighbors.
- Bert Spencer: Someone said,
it didn't tell the police that
Barbara lived ten
doors up the same road.
- David Wilson: She was
the secretary that you worked
with at the hospital.
- Bert Spencer: She was a
secretary at the hospital.
They didn't ask.
You know, I could have said,
"I've got green socks tonight.
I just had a poo in the
toilet," they didn't ask.
And I appreciate what
they were there for,
they were asking questions
and I answered the questions.
I answered every question.
- David Wilson: You continue to
campaign against people thinking
that you had anything
to do with that crime.
- Bert Spencer: I've
stopped that now.
Listen, I'm on camera.
I don't give a shit.
Think what you will.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
Despite the growing body
of circumstantial evidence
mounting against Bert,
a major breakthrough came in
the case when the police picked
up a gang of burglars who
would rob a nearby farm.
- Reporter: Police
picked up four men.
All known to them
as armed robbers.
Michael Hickey, Vincent, his
cousin and James Robinson.
A fourth, Pat Molloy.
- James D'Arcy: After
several days of interrogation,
one of the men,
Patrick Molloy,
admitted to being
at Yew Tree Farm.
He said he was upstairs
when he heard a gunshot
and when his accomplice,
16-year-old Michael
Hickey had accidentally
killed Carl with a shotgun.
Molloy's apparent confession led
to the rest of the gang turning
on each other.
This led to the successful
prosecution of the so-called
Bridgewater Four who
were found guilty and jailed
for between 12-25
years for the crime,
but there was one
person who was convinced
that they were innocent.
- Then as the teenager,
Michael Hickey, was led away,
his mother Anne, rushed to
the front of the gallery
and cried down tearfully,
"I'll fight, Michael.
I'll fight."
- James D'Arcy:
Michael Hickey's mother,
Anne Wheelan, began a
20-year-long campaign to free
the men and discover who
Carl's real killer could be.
And just four weeks after the
Bridgewater Four were jailed,
there was an
extraordinary development,
which immediately raised new
questions about who killed Carl.
- Reporter: Here, at
Holloway House Farm, a .5
mile from Yew Tree, again,
another brutal shotgun killing.
This time the victim was
a 70-year-old farmer
called Hubert Wilkes.
In the middle of a late
night social gathering,
Wilkes' close friend,
Hubert Spencer left the room,
returned with a
shotgun and killed him.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
The newsboy and the farmer
were killed in
neighboring farm houses,
and the coincidences
didn't end there.
Just like Carl, Hubert Wilkes,
was killed with a shotgun.
Just like Carl, he was shot
in the head at close range.
Just like Carl, he was
murdered while seated.
One man knew both
properties and both victims,
and that man was Bert Spencer.
♪ music playing ♪
Bert has no
explanation for why he murdered
Wilkes, but he does have
some memories of the night he
killed his best friend
and father figure.
- Bert Spencer: Little old man,
I loved him because he
was like a father.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
On December 13, 1979,
Hubert Wilkes hosted some
drinks at Holloway House Farm
for Bert's 40 birthday.
Present were farmer
Wilkes, his daughter Jean,
Bert and his wife, Janette.
- Bert Spencer: He got the
feeling that I was better
than his son, and eventually,
he started brining me
into the family.
A neatly and devout,
and cooked me a
Sunday lunch.
So, he was like a father figure
and that's where it hurts.
Now, my first wife, used
to do his bookkeeping.
She had said to me, she will
deny this, and I don't care.
She had said to me,
"Don't leave me
along with him."
Previously, had said to me, "Janette is being so loud.
I put my hand on her
thigh, and she wants me,
and doesn't
fucking want you."
He gave me all this,
all for about two years,
I took it.
Don't talk, it's just an old
man, but he was like a father.
I hadn't gotten my own dad and
then, we went down that night,
he came out all
bloody and blinding,
and the dog got to be
grabbed and put away.
Then he went and took down
the thing to another room
to do the books.
I sat in the lounge with
Jane, just general chat.
And Jane said, "It
is your birthday,
I bought you a present.
A little bit of pipe
tobacco, duty free."
"Thank you, Jane, "
I didn't kiss her,
I didn't love her.
I didn't want her.
She was sisterly-like.
Just a lovely girl, she was
studious, extremely proud.
When she was dressed
up, very proud.
"Thank you, love,
that's nice."
Pipe tobacco,
I smoked a pipe and previously,
Hubert Wilkes used
to brag--the farmers
used to get together,
and he'd mix special cocktails
to get their women pissed
and then have a swap around.
Thought nothing of it, but I
must've thought something of it.
I'd had a lot of whiskey
before I went in there
because it was my birthday.
I'd done a lot of whiskey.
I used to drink whiskey,
I don't know,
in case it makes me nasty.
Poured a drink, then he
stood up, and then he says,
in a great, big, loud voice,
I was nearly pissed now.
"Janette, I'd made
you a special cocktail."
And I cannot remember
what happened next, except,
I think I
fell down in a hallway,
and it was flash,
bang, wallop.
I know I feel down,
I do know.
Went out, apparently,
while I was out there,
I took his gun from the
door jamb, went to my car,
got a hack saw,
cut the barrel off.
I went in and Janette and Jean
said, "He walked in the room,
and rolled around the room.
Upright."
Then I went and shot him.
- James D'Arcy:
Burt's wife, Janette,
returned home in shock
and covered in blood.
She was met by her
terrified teenage daughter.
Bert's daughter is able to
recall what her mother said
the night her father
murdered Hubert Wilkes.
She has asked
not to be filmed.
"My mother said she got
up from the sitting,
and they had a fight.
As she was trying to
grab the gun off him,
he used the butts of
the gun and just constantly
hit her on
the top of her head.
And she ran off, and she ran
into the kitchen and my dad was
chasing her through her house,
and she hid under the table."
- Bert Spencer: I picked another
gun up, from another door jamb,
put it in my car,
I drove up the lane
and saw an ambulance.
"Oh, my mage,"
and I stopped.
I stopped.
It's all insane.
And a driver came up,
and he said,
"Bert, don't go down the lane, there's a gunman on the loose."
I said, Barry,
"I think it's me."
- James D'Arcy:
The death of Hubert Wilkes
saw Bert in
the dark for his murder.
- Bert Spencer: Okay, I
deserved to be put away,
but it wasn't intent.
I did what I did.
I'm so bloody sorry I did it,
but I didn't go there with a
gun, thinking,
"I'll kill the bastard."
It's just
something that bang,
it happened
because I was pissed.
Throughout his trial, Bert
Spencer, remained silent.
He never took the stand
and no explanation was ever
given for why he
had killed the farmer.
But watching the proceedings
closely was a woman with
a vested
interest in the case.
- Bert's Daughter: I remember
a lady looking at me,
every day, and smiling.
And it was Anne Wheelan.
She latched on to the
possibility that my father
could've been responsible
and not her son,
for killing the child.
- James D'Arcy: Bert was
sentenced to life in prison.
The striking similarities
between the murder of Carl
and Hubert Wilkes soon
became public knowledge.
This fueled the determination
of the Bridgewater Four campaign
group and their lawyers.
- There are a number
of coincidences,
which if there hadn't
been that second murder,
at the farm up the road, one
may never had known about it.
- James D'Arcy: One
of the condemned men,
started the longest rooftop
protest in prison history.
- Michael Hickey: Demonstrated
on the roof of Lestechers's
top security quarry prison.
Stating his case through a makeshift loud halo.
- James D'Arcy: Shouting his
innocence from the rooftops,
Hickey also yelled
the name of the man he
believed was guilty of
Carl's murder, Bert Spencer.
By now, Wheelan had
convinced the investigative
journalist Paul
Foote to join her cause.
With his help, Bert's name was
never out of the headlines.
Often, openly being accused
as Carl's real killer.
- Bert Spencer: These
alleged, what did I call them?
Celebrities.
The campaign group, it's
full of celebrities,
all trying to get me
hung for the crime.
They didn't know what
they were talking about,
but they--some of those
groups came to wear Wormwood
scrubs at 11:30
one night and outside,
and outside the big wall,
with a razor on it,
chanting up on the--you
can say, the windows.
Shouting, "Kill Bert
Spencer, Kill Bert Spencer.
Go Bridgewater,"
inciting the
inmates to kill me.
And you, members of that
campaign group, judge me.
I won't name you here, I
won't name and shame you here.
I may do, one day.
I may.
- James D'Arcy: Bert claims
that the barrage of accusations
meant his own life
was in constant danger
whilst in prison,
and he was left with no option,
but to turn
to violence or die
at the hands
of other inmates.
- David Wilson: You were
a convicted murderer,
you--body builder, were you
the top of the hierarchy?
Were you the--the
daddy of the way?
- Bert Spencer: Not purposely.
Not purposely.
No, I used to protect
people, there are bullies.
There's actually rapists in
male prisons, did you know that?
- David Wilson: Yeah.
- Bert Spencer:
You must know that.
There--barbaric bastards.
♪ music playing ♪
We had a young Philippine
kid that was raped
in our adult wither ,
3-4 got a hold of him
and--I went to town.
- David Wilson: What did you do?
- Bert Spencer: I just went
in like a bloody bulldozer.
I dealt with it.
I stopped it.
When somebody goes
off a young kid,
and they got long hair and
bloody pigtails and shaved
in ras clad, the bumba
clad, I went in, mate.
I just went--I don't know.
I didn't ever think about it.
I just went in and--I'm not
proud of what I had to
do in my sentence.
On occasions, I did it.
I did it, and I stopped it.
And then I got a reputation,
I ran the bloody prison.
I just wasnt'
afraid of anyone.
- James D'Arcy: Whilst Bert says
he ruled the other inmates
with an iron fist, something
were beyond his control.
- Bert Spencer: When I was in
Wormwood scrubs, my dad died.
And they took me out,
all the way to Birmingham,
Sully Oak, to the funeral.
Handcuffed all the way,
you know about this
because you
were the governor.
When I got there, the three
screws that were escorting me.
Total strangers, they didn't
know and they said,
"Right, Bert.
We don't know you.
Don't do anything
stupid."
I said,
"What are you talking about?
I'm not going
to do anything stupid."
They said, "Well,
we're going to uncuff you."
I said, "Do it."
♪ music playing ♪
Throughout the service,
the priest kept staring
at me.
I'm not paranoid,
and I didn't mind that,
and the priest came to me
afterwards, and he said,
"When I went and saw the coffin,
I thought I was looking at you."
- James D'Arcy:
Whilst in prison,
Bert claims that he was
continually silenced
and unable to defend himself against accusations
that he murdered Carl.
This feeling of being ganged at
the time, continues to rile him.
- Bert Spencer: I've
waited 30 years for this.
I've been suppressed, I've
been gagged, I've been shot on,
kicked while I was down.
I'm standing up now.
Come and have a kick!
I'm different now.
- David Wilson: Will it be
light for you if people who
watch the program listen
to what you're arguing.
Weigh it all up
and still say,
"Yeah, he killed
Carl Bridgewater."
- Bert Spencer: Okay.
Can you come forward with the
slightest fragment of evidence?
Because we deal with
evidence in courts.
We don't deal
with newspapers.
We deal with evidence.
Can you prove it?
But I am standing up now,
you can't trample over me.
Be careful--what
you say against me.
I might
retaliate in the courts.
- David Wilson: I want
to come back and reflect.
After I've reflected on this
first meeting and talked
to you about other
things that struck me
about the conversation
we've had today.
Is that okay?
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: Great.
- David Wilson: Well,
thank you very much, Bert,
for agreeing to see me,
and I'll see you again soon.
- Bert Spencer: You're
more than welcome anytime.
- David Wilson: Thank you
and let's reflect on some
of the things
that we discussed.
Bits that--you know, we
need to think about again.
All the bits we need to cover,
and I'll look forward
to seeing you.
- Bert Spencer: Look forward to
seeing you again, safe journey.
- David Wilson: Thank you.
- Bert Spencer: Come up, here.
- David Wilson: Take care.
Bye, Christine.
- Bert Spencer: Safe journey.
- Christine: Bye.
Bye.
- David Wilson: Go in!
It's cold.
I'm developing a
picture of Bert.
I don't want to
easily jump to labels,
but there were some
huge narcissism.
Some huge--"I'm going
to speak to the nation.
I'm going to have my
justification for my behavior."
We need to check the materials
in relation to his movements
on the day that Carl
Bridgewater died.
I, therefore, would quite
like to speak to Barbara.
He was going to mention her as
quickly as possible and move on,
and yet, this was a woman
who basically has stood
up his alibi about
being in Colbertl Hospital
on the day Carl Bridgewater died, for decades!
So, it's her, really, I'd
be quite keen to talk to.
Given that Bert is so
extroverted about other
people in the story.
Barbara, no matter how central,
mentioned and then ignored,
very quickly.
I quite like to speak to her.
Bert--Bert is just coming
behind us with another dog.
So, do you know whose
dog it is, Bert?
- Bert Spencer: We're going
to find out, op there.
Come on, babe.
In there, love.
In there.
- David Wilson: That's what is
going at his mind at the minute.
He wants to know
exactly what I think.
He wants to know if
he passed the test.
There he goes.
The hero in his own mind.
Animal lover, child lover.
Killer.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
As a convicted murderer,
Bert served the full
term of 14 years for killing
Hubert Wilkes.
He received no parole because
he would never satisfactorily
explain why he had
murdered the farmer.
On his release, Bert,
drifted away into obscurity,
but any hopes he had of a
quiet life were dashed when
the Bridgewater Four's
conviction was quashed,
and they were
made free men.
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
And it was the circumstantial
evidence against Bert Spencer,
which featured prominently in
the defense counsel's arguments
during the court appeals.
- Female Reporter: Mr.
Bennet Heightner, QC,
spoke about a man seen by
police after the murder,
called Herbert Spencer.
Mr. Spencer had also failed
to disclose that he knew
Carl Bridgewater,
that he bought and sold
antiques and that he
had permission to shoot
birds at Yew Tree Farm.
- James D'Arcy: With Carl's
killer still walking free,
Bert Spencer, once again,
found himself being asked
difficult questions about
the newspaper boy's death.
- Male Reporter: Joining me now
are Bert Spencer who has been
accused of killing Carl
Bridgewater, his wife Christina,
and Anne Wheelan,
Michael Hickey's mother.
Do you now feel the need
to get involved in the search
to find that man.
- Anne Wheelan I won't rest.
Let's put it like this,
until the perpetrator of that
child--the killing of
that child is behind bars.
I mean, he has been
accused of this by prisoners,
seven times, at least.
- Male Reporter: Now, after
reading that, this morning,
a lot of people are going
to draw the conclusion
that you killed
Carl Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer: A
lot of people are,
but nothing keeps the spotlight
off me while there is
people like Anne Wheelan
pointing her finger at me.
I do not fear any
police investigation,
I would welcome one.
- Anne Wheelan: It wasn't
me that accused you in
the very first place.
I want to finish, please.
Is this not a fact?
You did have guns.
Is this not a fact, you
were an antique dealer?
lived next door to the child,
and you refused to
tell the police that?
Is this not a fact that
your car was seen turning
into Yew Tree Farm?
The police went out and in
a 50-mile radius to look
for Vauxhall Viva, they came
out with a few, Vauxhall Viva.
Is this a fact that
you were the only man in
uniform that was
found and it happened to
be the man--is this
a fact when they went
to your house,
and you could've said,
"Go and see my colleague
Mrs. --,
she will give you an alibi."
Is this not a fact,
your papers have gone missing?
- Bert Spencer: Don't
lie on this program.
- Anne Wheelan: She
went to the hospital.
Mr. Spencer, I have this,
and I don't need papers.
I have--well, I'm sorry,
this has to be sorted out.
- Male Reporter:
This is not a court.
- Bert Spencer: Alright.
- Male Reporter: Neither
is it trial by media,
but let me
ask you one question.
For the record--
- Bert Spencer: Alright, ask it.
- Male Reporter: Did you
shoot Carl Bridgewater?
- Bert Spencer: I did not
and that is on the record
and no attempts by these people,
nor a mountain of attempts
is going to remove
it from the record.
Talking about facts,
that, lady, is fact.
- James D'Arcy: During the
course of the campaign to
free the Bridgewater
Four, Anne Wheelan,
accumulated thousands
of legal documents.
She believed they may
hold clues to help catch
Carl Bridgewater's killer.
David Wilson has been
given unrestricted access
to the materials.
- David Wilson: And are all
these boxes related to the case?
- Anne Wheelan: Yes, cabinets.
All those boxes, and the boxes
all behind and everything.
It's crystal clear in some
of these boxes that you see,
that the evidence is there
to convict the person that's
responsible for
the horrific murder.
Yeah.
Psychopath, I think he is.
So, that's what
I'm hoping, anyway.
- David Wilson: Anne, you've
been incredibly vocal about
saying that Bert Spencer was
responsible for Carl's murder.
Why do you think
he's never sued you?
- Anne Wheelan:
Because he did it!
Because he's guilty.
If he sues me, he takes me into
a court of law, doesn't he?
- David Wilson: The quashing of
those convictions, inevitably,
put the spotlight back
on to Bert Spencer.
You met him a few times,
how did those encounters go?
- Anne Wheelan: I find
him, personally, again,
a personal feeling this
is, quite a chilling man.
- David Wilson: How does
Bert Spencer react to you
on a personal level?
- Anne Wheelan: Oh, most of
the time, wishes me dead.
It's the best thing
that could happen to me.
So, and I'll tell
you why, I think,
because he knows
that I'm right.
I've got a feeling he
wants to be challenged.
He knows he's guilty,
I think he's playing
a game with everybody.
With everyone.
- David Wilson: Why is he
brining it all back up now,
after all these years?
- Anne Wheelan: I think
he wants to be found out.
He wants to be found out.
- David Wilson: Do you think
he's trying to confess?
- Anne Wheelan: He
wants to confess,
but he wants somebody to
really--like he's--like
he's playing a tough
game with people,
he wants that tough game
played back with him.
He wants it dragged out
of him because he's not
normal in the head.
He's not a normal person.
I know, I just know,
I'm not just pointing a
finger because of the sake
of it, but in my eyes,
Bert Spencer killed
Carl Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer: I don't want
to speak to Anne Wheelan.
I have no interest,
whatsoever, in my life.
She is not even part of
my life, she's a nothing.
I actually hate the bitch.
I worship the ground
she has coming to her.
Horrible bitch.
Her boy did it.
I am absolutely convinced.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
Coming up next time.
Professor Wilson learns more
about Bert's association with
the place
where Carl was killed.
- David Wilson: The
police officer says,
"Have you visited
Yew Tree Farm?"
Spencer replied, "Yes, I have.
You found out."
- James D'Arcy:
David and Bert embark on a
remarkable road trip, returning
to the scene of the crime.
- David Wilson: What do
you think Carl might say
back to you?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know.
I really don't.
What do you think he might say?
- David Wilson: He might
say you killed him.
- James D'Arcy: And the relation
between the two men
reach breaking point.
- Bert Spencer: Is he trying to
tie me into Carl Bridgewater,
and it feels
as though he is.
I wasn't' t there.
I wasn't guilty, and now
he's raising it all up again.
That criminalizes me.
I could be bloody arrested.
criminologist professor
David Wilson riles Bert as he
questions him about whether
he had any role in the murder
of Carl Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer:
Listen, I'm on camera.
I don't give a shit.
Think what you will.
- James D'Arcy: Professor Wilson
becomes convinced that
Bert's alibi
demands closer scrutiny.
- David Wilson: This was a woman
who basically has stood up
his alibi about being
in Colbert Hospital,
on the day that Carl
Bridgewater died for decades.
- James D'Arcy: And could
Bert be playing a game
of psychological chess
with the professor?
- Anne Wheelan: He
knows he's guilty.
I think he's playing
a game with everybody.
- Bert Spencer: That should go
in the compost with many people,
you just strip the leaves
off, and you plant it,
and you will produce a life.
A living thing.
I don't want to lose it.
I've cut it now, I'll just
poke it in there, look.
I appreciate life,
living things,
human beings
and life itself.
Okay?
I took a life.
I'm fully aware of
the awfulness of that.
♪ music playing ♪
Okay?
- James D'Arcy: On
December 13, 1979,
just four weeks after the
Bridgewater Four had been
jailed, another murder took
place at a Farmhouse just
500 yards from where
Carl was murdered.
The victim was local farmer
Hubert Wilkes, but this time,
the killer was caught at
the scene of the crime.
His name is Bert Spencer.
The murder of Hubert Wilkes
was almost a carbon copy
of the murder of Carl.
Both victims were shot in the
side of the head while seated,
at point-blank range
with the shotgun,
but Bert believes he was made
a scapegoat for Carl's murder
by the campaign group
determined to see
the Bridgewater Four
released, and he has strong
views on
forgiving and forgetting.
- Bert Spencer: We go to
church--I go to church.
That's hard to believe
for some of you.
I go to church and I say, with
you, the Lord's prayer, okay.
Oh, the wind blew that up.
Look.
Now, I have to question the rest
of the world, why do you say it?
Why do you--why are you two
faced liars when you talk
to your God concept?
Why on earth in the
Lord's prayer, do you say?
"Dear Lord, our
Father in Heaven.
Hallowed be thy name--"
and then further
down the prayer,
"Forgive us our trespasses,"
good, "And forgive us,
as we forgive those
who trespass against us."
What a load of
liars we are, as a nation.
We will not forgive those
who trespass against us,
we want revenge.
No one gets forgiven.
Why do we have courts?
Prosecutions?
We don't forgive, but
we say to our God,
"We will forgive those who
trespass against us."
All of those people, who
joined a campaign group,
to persecute me and mentally
torture me for all those years,
why didn't you forgive me?
I've never done
anything against you.
I think that answers
the question.
You're liars, you are two
faced, as you talk to your God,
and he will do something
about it one day.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy: During
the course of the campaign
to free the
Bridgewater Four, Anne Wheelan,
the mother of one of
those wrongly accused,
accumulated thousands
of legal documents.
She believes they may help
catch Carl Bridgewater's killer
and has handed them over
to criminologist professor
David Wilson.
- David Wilson: Now, are all
these boxes related to the case?
- Anne Wheelan: Yes.
- James D'Arcy: Professor Wilson
has been invited to speak to
Bert, who is determined to
put to rest rumors that he was
involved in Carl's murder.
With an archive of over 10,000
documents in his possession,
David Wilson has assembled a
team of criminology researchers
to begin the critical and
painstaking task of sifting
through the documents in
order to identify anything of
importance that could lead
him closer to understanding
what happened to Carl,
the day he was killed.
- David Wilson: This is
old-fashioned research.
In these boxes are documents
collected over the course of
20 years by Anne Wheelan,
who is the mother of
Michael Hickey,
one of the Bridgewater Four.
The documents are
trial transcripts,
police witness statements,
newspaper cuttings,
prison correspondence.
Frankly, they are a treasure
trove of information
and I believe that in
these boxes is the identity
of the killer
of Carl Bridgewater.
- James D'Arcy:
Searching the papers,
the researcher soon uncover
documents that professor
Wilson believes may
be of real importance.
- David Wilson: This is
the very first statement
that Spencer is
going to make to the police
in relation to the murder
of Carl Bridgewater
and this is the alibi.
Here is his alibi.
8:30 until 5:10.
He's claiming he was at
the hospital all day.
That's his alibi.
This alibi is what
protects Bert Spencer.
- James D'Arcy: Bert Spencer has
always relied on one piece of
evidence, when there is any
suggestion that he may have
been involved in the killing
of Carl Bridgewater.
The fact that his
secretary, Barbara,
provided him with
a cast iron alibi.
Bert worked as an ambulance
officer at Colbert Hospital
and his secretary Barbara
gave a statement saying that
he had been
at work all day.
- Melinda: David, I
just got something here.
Earlier on, Barbara said
that Bert wouldn't
ever leave the hospital,
but it's mentioned here that
he might leave for lunch
around 1 PM or
either earlier or later--
- David Wilson: Melinda,
this is very important.
Look, except for, perhaps,
leaving for lunch!
"Sometimes he had lunch a little
bit earlier, or a bit later,
and he may have
done on that day.
He was upset and
worried at the time,
by the attention given to him
by the police."
This is really important, Melinda, well done.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy: The ongoing search of the documents
turns up another
compelling piece of information.
All ambulance officers who
worked at Colbert Hospital kept
timesheets in a log filed
away at the end of each month.
They provided the exact
whereabouts of employees in
the jobs they
were succumbed to.
These logs could've
supported Bert's alibi,
had they not
mysteriously disappeared.
- A police officer has gone
and looked at the ambulance's
daily record sheets
and unfortunately
on the date
of Carl's murder,
the record
sheets are missing.
- James D'Arcy: Bert as a
senior ambulance officer,
was one of the few people at
Colbert Hospital who would've
had access to these records.
He maintains that corrupt police
officers could have removed
the records and logbooks
in a bid to make him a
scapegoat for Carl
Bridgewater's murder.
As the search through
the documents continues,
unearthed is the complete
police transcript of the second
interview conducted with
Bert at Colbert Hospital.
Taking place almost a week
after the first interview,
Bert's opening line to
detectives suggests that he was
expecting to see them again.
- David Wilson: Go back
to the very start of it.
- The very start.
- David Wilson: Look what
he says here that the police
officer says, "I made known
to him the reason for my visit
and said, "Have you
visited Yew Tree Farm?
Spencer replied, "Yes, I have.
You found out."
- James D'Arcy:
When asked if he'd ever been
to Yew Tree Farm in
uniform, Bert replied,
"I think so."
In his first
statement, Bert Spencer,
didn't tell police that he had
at one point lived only a
few doors away from
Carl Bridgewater.
In his second interview,
the police pushed Bert on how
well they knew each other.
- David Wilson: That's a
very odd statement, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- David Wilson: "I
didn't recognize him, "
is he meaning the press
photographs or is he actually
in Yew Tree Farm that day?
Does Carl Bridgewater have to
die for the simple instrumental
reason that Bert
didn't recognize him,
but Carl recognized Bert.
- James D'Arcy:
Professor Wilson wonders,
could this have been the true
motive for Carl's murder?
- David Wilson: Well, I wondered
if we were going to find
these in the boxes,
at some stage.
These are actually the crime
scene photographs themselves
of Carl after
he had been murdered.
So, they are
truly appalling.
So, I think
we'll just stop.
She shouldn't
be filming this.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
Having been through Anne
Wheelan's files,
professor Wilson,
returns to speak
to Bert once more.
Determined to ask him
about the new information
he has uncovered.
- David Wilson: I see you
got your wainscot again,
that's good.
- Bert Spencer: Are you
jealous you haven't gotten one?
- David Wilson: Very jealous.
- Bert Spencer: That's
a different wainscot,
I got about a dozen,
I love them
- David Wilson: Do you think your wainscot and your garden
tell the same
story about the man
who is Bert Spencer?
You like to stand out
from the crowd, don't you?
- Bert Spencer: No,
no, no, no, no, no, no.
I'm just--I'm old-fashioned,
that' a wainscot is.
I'm made edwardian
maybe Victorian, no
edwardian , and the garden
is just--that's my hobby.
I don't stand out.
- David Wilson: You don't
think this stands out from
the other gardens
in the village?
- Bert Spencer: Yes, it does.
That wasn't the idea
when I built it.
This is a cycling route, and
you get crowds of cyclists,
and we get
people from Denmark.
They stopped there, about three
days ago, and one of them said,
"He has a whole museum!"
- David Wilson: It's true.
- Bert Spencer: But it
wasn't designed for that.
It's just, I like
it, it's lovely.
Christine likes it.
I like it,
I like gardening.
- David Wilson: Where
can we go for a walk.
- Bert Spencer: At the park!
- David Wilson: Come on
then, you lead the way.
I kept coming back
to two things.
Why now?
Why do you want to
talk about this now?
- Bert Spencer: I wanted
to talk about it 30 years
ago but was suppressed.
I couldn't!
I wasn't' allowed to.
- David Wilson: Yeah?
Who wouldn't allow
you to talk about it?
- Bert Spencer: The prison.
In ---, I had a bundle
of papers that were
going to be
what was in my manuscript.
Things I had replied, noted,
and they snatched them
out of my hand.
You are not allowed to
write or say about prison,
or anybody else's crime
or your own crime.
Does that
answer your question?
I wasn't allowed to.
I am today.
I'm free.
- David Wilson: Why do you
think they wanted to cover up?
- Bert Spencer: I think they
were really sure--was Bert
involved, wasn't he?
That's the feeling I got.
I thought it was me
against the world.
I really did.
Even the coppers.
I thought it was me against
the world and that's how
I lived for a few years.
I was at
war against the world.
- David Wilson: Do you
think you're a bit paranoid?
- Bert: No.
I think I'm not.
- David Wilson: Being at
war, "Me against the world, "
is paranoia.
- Bert Spencer: Yeah, but
look at every newspaper.
Look--when I did get a chance
to see a television, I'm on it.
It's people that like saying,
"The records are missing."
- Bert Spencer: So, what?
I'm in prison.
Someone took them.
- David Wilson: The
records--these are the records
that would have shown your
movements on the day that
Carl Bridgewater
was murdered and those records
by going missing weren't
able to corroborate what
it was that you
said about where you were
because your argument
is that you were at Colbert
Hospital all day.
- Bert Spencer: But
they weren't necessary.
A lot was made of them.
- David Wilson: What
was in the records?
What might have been
something that could
exonerate you completely?
- Bert Spencer: Yes, yes.
- David Wilson: Something in
the book--might have been
something that would have
incriminated you completely.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: So, the records
going missing is quite important
in terms of the story that
we've been discussing.
- Bert Spencer: It is,
but if there was something
in that book that
could incriminate me,
why didn't they give
it to the news media?
"We got him!"
- David Wilson: Because
it was you that took it.
That's their argument!
Their argument is that it
was you that took the book.
- Bert Spencer: You
couldn't get in.
You can't get in.
- David Wilson: But you knew
the headquarters really well,
didn't you?
- Bert Spencer: I
knew it really well.
- David Wilson: You definitely
were at Colbert Hospital
all day.
- Bert: All day.
- David Wilson: All day?
- Bert: Every minute of
that day and it was proven, so--
- David Wilson: Well, it
hasn't been proven because
the thing that could
prove that Bert,
were the records and the
records went missing.
- James D'Arcy: Bert had
a cast iron alibi at the time
in his secretary Barbara.
She was able to testify that
Bert had been at Colbert
Hospital all day on the
day Carl was killed.
This would see the heat
of the police investigation
taken off Bert.
- David Wilson: Bert, were you
always faithful to your wives?
- Bert Spencer: No.
- David Wilson:
You played around?
- Bert Spencer: I played around
with someone I thought
I had fallen in love with.
- David Wilson: Is
that woman still alive?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know.
I don't know.
I mean, I've made no attempt
to rekindle as it were,
I don't know.
- David Wilson: What
period of time was that?
When were
you having an affair?
- Bert Spencer: Just before
I committed my offense.
- David Wilson: So,
in the late 70s?
- Bert Spencer: I
was getting on a bit.
- David Wilson: So that was
when you were still married
to your
first wife, Janette?
- Bert: Yes.
Yes.
- David Wilson: Bert, will
you be even more honest with
me and tell me who you were
having an affair with?
- Bert Spencer: No,
because--no, I won't.
- David Wilson: Is
this woman still alive?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know.
I really don't know, no.
- David Wilson: Was
it a work colleague?
- Bert Spencer: No.
She was lovely.
We melted, and we parted,
and she was so lovely,
I wouldn't upset
her life, you know?
It was lovely.
It was lovely, it really was.
- David Wilson: I'm worried
that you're getting cold.
- Bert Spencer: I am cold, yes.
- David Wilson: So, let's
go back to the house.
- Bert Spencer: I am cold.
Yeah.
- James D'Arcy:
Back in the house,
David Wilson gets the
chance to speak to Bert's
current partner, Christine.
- Christine: He said, I've got
something I've got to tell you.
He said, I've been
in prison for murder.
First off, I didn't know
really which way to think
because I never came across
somebody like this before,
and being the first time,
I was a bit apprehensive.
I didn't know if Bert was
still the same person or
if his lifestyle had changed.
Whether he was still violent
or if he was still in the same
mood, sort of thing.
When Bert explained things to
me, what he--what he had done,
and then when the
police contacted him,
it was--they were putting 2
and 2 together and making 5,
but they couldn't deduct
anything from it because things
were going, dropping into place,
which I'd say as a --not as a
policeman or a detective, but
I would have said, "Blue car,
Bert's got a blue car.
Person in uniform,
Bert wears a uniform.
Knows the family?
Bert knows the family."
He knew where
they lived, well,
3/3 makes a story.
- David Wilson: Who
is Bert Spencer?
- Bert Spencer: Bert Spencer
is, I am my daddy's boy.
He was a nasty,
hard bastard.
- David Wilson: Are
you a nasty, hard?
- Bert Spencer: That's me.
- David Wilson: Are you
a nasty, hard bastard?
- Bert Spencer: No, but
I'm his boy, aren't I?
- David Wilson: So, the apple
never falls too far
from the tree?
Is that
what you're arguing?
- Bert Spencer:
Possibly, I don't know.
If you jump on my
back, you'll get hurt.
Okay?
If you don't jump on my back,
I will love you
and treat you out.
Don't attack me,
because I am my daddy's boy,
and it'll come out.
Just not angry, you know.
Is it?
- David Wilson: No, it
feels like a threat.
- Bert Spencer: Shut up.
- David Wilson:
It does, it does.
It feels like a threat, brother.
- Bert Spencer: No, no.
You asked me a question,
I'm trying to answer it.
- David Wilson: Oh yeah.
- Bert Spencer: Who am I?
- David Wilson: You
answered it very clearly.
- Bert Spencer: I did.
- David Wilson: You did.
- Bert Spencer: I meant it.
- David Wilson: I understood
what you were arguing.
- Bert Spencer: It's
not threatening you.
It's not threatening anyone.
If anyone jumps on my back
with aggression in mind,
I can deal with it
like my dad did.
I am my daddy's boy.
- David Wilson: But
if we cross your back,
if those people cross that--
- Bert Spencer: You can cross.
I like it with you,
I want to hurt you.
I like you.
I'll question, I'll discuss.
I wouldn't hurt
you; you've done it.
You've crossed that barrier.
I won't hurt you.
I'll discuss with you.
I'll question--I'll
question you.
I'll question anybody.
- David Wilson: What does
it mean to be labeled
as a murderer?
- Bert Spencer:
Just stop a minute.
If you could switch off time
and go back in time, to 1978,
yeah--1978, what would
you have changed from your
life at that point?
- Bert Spencer: I would
have been away on holiday.
Away from the West Midlands.
- David Wilson:
Bad memories in 78?
- Bert Spencer: Stop.
Bloody hell.
- David Wilson: If you
want to stop, you can stop.
- Bert Spencer: Just stop.
- David Wilson: Yeah.
It was a
truly remarkable day.
I mean, the kinds of things
he's revealing in the course
of the interview
are some of the things
he's never
publicly stated before.
He's told me that at the time
that he murdered Hubert Wilkes,
he was having an affair.
And therefore, this whole
wife swapping alibi
becomes more tenuous.
You know, why do you care so
much about the woman that
you've actually betrayed
by having an affair,
and you say she was having an
affair at that time, as well.
But the most remarkable thing
of all is the sense that
he's putting
himself forward again.
He's inserting himself into a
drama about his life
and his role in the murder
of Carl Bridgewater.
I mean, you know,
fair credit to him,
I keep trying to explain to him
that people will look at this,
and he calls
it trial by media.
But actually, it's
him that's called.
It's him that set
himself up as a cord.
He's put himself in the dog.
- James D'Arcy: As a former
prison governor, David Wilson,
was trained to perform a
detailed checklist on prisoners
he suspected of showing
signs of psychopathy.
This is known as a P Scan.
- David Wilson: What
I'll do tonight is,
I'm going to do a P Scan on him,
which is simply looking to
see if based on the things
that he's written,
the performances in terms of
TV, my own knowledge now
of him through some 20
hours of interview.
Am I dealing with somebody
who's psychopathic?
- James D'Arcy: Following
the last encounter,
Bert calls the filmmakers to
tell them he is unhappy with
the line of questioning.
- Bert Spencer: I haven't
slept for two nights,
thinking about it.
You tell me to delve on
this and delve on that.
I'm not happy with him,
he's all to do with multiple
psychotic killers.
Is he trying
to make me one?
Is he trying to tie me
into Carl Bridgewater?
And it feels
as though he is.
I wasn't there, I wasn't guilty,
and now he's raising it
all up again.
That criminalizes me.
I can be bloody arrested.
I am a lifer.
He's got me
on trial by media.
I want to ask him face to face,
"What are you out to achieve
from this broadcast?"
- James D'Arcy: Journalist
and writer, Simon Golding,
has been working on
an account of Bert's life
for the past two years.
Simon introduced
David Wilson to Bert.
As tensions mount following
the last interview,
Bert has asked
Simon to visit him,
to discuss the tone of
David Wilson's questioning.
- Simon Golding: Professor
David Wilson will conduct
his inquiry as he feels fit,
and he wants to be as
open as possible,
and the only way I think
Bert is going to really get something out of this,
"Are we going
to move forward, "
is if Bert is
open and truthful.
Bert, you seemed quite concerned
about professor David Wilson
and the interview, and how it's
actually going at the moment.
And I, obviously, feel that you
are not very happy about it
and the direction it's going
in, is that correct?
- Bert Spencer: He's
a criminologist,
and he's good at his job.
Nice enough bloke, but he seems
to be--his role seems to be
incriminating people,
whoever he's talking about
and when he was talking to me,
I felt that there was
some of that coming out in him, as though he was trying to
incriminate me
without even knowing it.
I've had enough of that, I've
had it for years, and years,
I don't want anymore.
- Simon Golding: Is it the
questioning or is it the--do you
feel he's accusing you?
Or what seems to be
the root problem?
- Bert Spencer: One of the
things he brought up, okay,
was I having an affair?
- Bert Spencer: I
should have said, "Well,
what's it got to do with you?"
I said, "Yes.
Yes, I had an affair, but
it wasn't really an affair,
it was a fling.
I won't give you
the person's name, "
but that seemed to be a
stumbling block because if it
happened to be my secretary,
at work, people would say,
"She's covered up for him."
It was not
my secretary at work.
The police know that.
They interviewed her, they
put her through a riddle.
Microscopically,
in case it was her.
No, it wasn't.
We were just friends
and workmates.
- Simon Golding: I think you
should use this opportunity
for you to actually fire back,
like you are talking to me now,
is to do that with
professor Wilson.
- Bert Spencer: Right.
- Simon Golding: And be open
and when you actually make
those--make those points
because you're not
on trial here,
you're just giving your chance,
you know,
to mention something.
- Bert Spencer: Yeah, okay,
but that's what I'd like.
I'd like something else to, sort
of cement in people's minds
that I am telling the truth.
At the moment, it's
just me saying so.
Okay?
I happen to be a Quaker.
I do tell the truth and one
point the public might like
to concede their ears,
if ever I have to go to court as
a witness for anything,
I don't have to take the oath.
I'm a Quaker.
I am expected
to tell the truth.
Now, this--this phenomenon
that we're discussing
is a major part of my life.
It's not just something
silly, or minor.
It's a major
part of my life.
Very important to me.
I have to tell the truth.
And I'd like some--something
to corroborate that.
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy:
The last encounter between
the two men ended with Bert
breaking down, however,
Bert has invited David Wilson to
meet him again, but this time,
in even more extraordinary
circumstances.
- David Wilson: Hi, Bert.
- Bert Spencer:
Hello, again, David.
- David Wilson:
Yeah, how are you?
- James D'Arcy: The two
men are in Staffordshire.
It is the first time that Bert
has returned to the area since
he murdered Hubert Wilkes.
- Bert Spencer: We've
got a lot to do.
- David Wilson: Yes.
- Bert Spencer:
Let's get on then.
- James D'Arcy: The first
place the two men visit is
the cul-de-sac where
Bert used to live.
A few doors away from
Carl Bridgewater.
Bert lived as a neighbor
of the Bridgewater's
for almost 8 years.
Carl literally grew up on
the street where Bert lived.
- Bert Spencer: Somewhere
here Carl lived.
One of these houses and--we
lived in that one there.
- David Wilson: Which one?
- Bert Spencer: That
one there, look.
- David Wilson: And Carl lived?
- Bert: Somewhere there.
- David Wilson: So,
one, two, three, four,
five doors away is
Carl Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer: Yeah.
Yeah.
- David Wilson: Gosh,
I can't even imagine.
See, this is why I am so
interested to be here.
I can't have imagined it
was going to be really big.
- Bert Spencer: No, this was it.
- David Wilson:
It's very intimate.
- Bert Spencer: This
was a kids' playground.
- David Wilson: All the
kids play with each other?
- Bert Spencer: Yeah, here.
And my daughter.
Yeah, here.
- David Wilson: And Carl?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know
because I didn't' play with him,
I don't know who they were.
- David Wilson: Yeah?
- Bert: There were groups of
kids from all around this area,
playing here.
- David Wilson: But you have
no memory of Carl, well?
- Bert Spencer: No, when I saw
Carl's picture in the paper,
I thought, "Yeah, they
all look like that.
They all--''I hope no one is
offended about the way I talk.
I'm not offending anyone.
It was just a kid
playing with other kids,
it meant nothing to me.
That's said in the
nicest possible way.
I didn't know him.
I didn't play with him.
- David Wilson: And you
would move from here,
when Carl was 10, and then he
was 13 when he was murdered.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
I was--
- David Wilson: So,
there are three years in between
you living here and--
- Bert Spencer:
And Kingsley Road.
- David Wilson:
And Kingsley Road?
- Bert Spencer: Yeah.
It's lovely to come back,
it's--it's lovely to come back.
You're flabbergasted.
- David Wilson:
I'm flabbergasted.
- Bert Spencer: Why?
- David Wilson: Well,
I kind of thought this would
be really emotional.
- Bert Spencer: No, it isn't.
It's lovely to come back
and see how nice this
place has been made.
- James D'Arcy: The next place
they visit is Yew Tree Farm
where Carl Bridgewater
was murdered in 1978.
Whilst he has always denied
involvement in Carl's murder,
he has never denied that
he had been inside the farmhouse
on at least three occasions, admired the antique furnishings
and had also frequently
accessed the land for
farming and shooting.
- David Wilson: Oh,
gosh, this is it.
Oh my gosh.
- Bert Spencer: Look at this.
Crikey.
I was down here
hundreds of times.
- David Wilson:
Hundreds of times.
You knew the farm well.
- Bert Spencer: Oh, crikey, yes.
- David Wilson: And had you
been inside the farmhouse?
- Bert Spencer:
Yes, I had, I had.
- David Wilson: How many times?
- Bert Spencer:
About two, three.
I've been in, and I've
been in and spoke to them,
and sat down with them.
Cup of tea with them.
Little old couple, very nice.
- David Wilson: And the
couple that lived here,
they were quite elderly.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
They didn't go
out--they didn't go out.
I knew people came; I
knew the doctor came.
I knew someone delivered
papers, but not who.
- David Wilson: Why did
they go out that day?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know,
apparently--I don't really know.
I think it was some
sort of treat for them.
I don't really know that because
they didn't really go out.
- David Wilson: Yeah, what's it
feel like to be standing outside
the place that's--you know,
your name is attached.
- Bert Spencer: I know.
I know.
- David Wilson: To the story of
the farm that once stood here
- Bert Spencer: I know.
It doesn't really feel strange,
I used to work up and down here.
- David Wilson:
If Carl was alive,
or you could speak
to Carl Bridgewater,
what is it you would
like to say to him?
- Bert Spencer: Well--
- David Wilson: Go on.
- Bert Spencer: 35 years ago,
because of two horrific
murder cases that happened
in this vicinity,
your name and mine became
intrinsically joined.
You are welcome
in my life, Carl,
but how I wish--how I wish we
could've been fused together
under different and
happier circumstances.
Through the power
of silent prayer,
I have spoken to and prayed
for you, Carl, many times.
That's what I'd say to you.
God bless you.
- David Wilson: And what
do you think Carl might say
back to you?
- Bert Spencer: I don't know.
I really don't.
I don't know,
that's--I don't know,
what do you think he might say?
- David Wilson: He might
say you killed him.
- Bert Spencer: He might,
but he would know that
it would be a lie.
He wouldn't say that.
He was apparently a nice, little
boy scout, he wouldn't lie.
- David Wilson: Why do you
think he got murdered that day?
- Bert Spencer: Well, I can
only go on what the police said.
It was a robbery and
it got disturbed.
There was a robbery in progress.
- David Wilson: Robbers don't
normally shoot 13-year-old boys.
- Bert Spencer: No, no.
Neither do ambulance
men, thank you very much.
Point taken?
- David Wilson: Ambulance
men don't normally shoot
their best friends.
- Bert Spencer: And
ambulance men, David,
don't go on armed robberies in
full dress uniform to places
where they are very well known.
That's the point I
want you to understand.
I wouldn't shoot a boy.
There's no way I could even--
- David Wilson: It's for me,
he was shot because
he could
identify his killer.
- Bert Spencer: That's
what the police say.
- David Wilson: I would say,
I saw, looking at the evidence,
I would say that.
I would say, it's very unusual
for a robber to shoot a
13-year-old boy.
- Bert Spencer: I know what
you're thinking but let me just
make this perfectly clear.
I would not have, under
any circumstances,
come in an armed robbery to a
farm I thought people were in
and where I was known,
and I knew someone
delivered papers now.
- David Wilson: Maybe you
weren't doing an armed robbery.
I'm not saying you were
doing an armed robbery;
you could have been
doing anything.
You could have been--you spotted
something when you were in the
house, you liked those foxes,
you could've been taking things
that--to sell on.
And Carl Bridgewater, because
the back door was open,
was used to walking in if
the back door was open because
he would hand deliver the
papers to the elderly couple.
That's what is in
the police statement.
So, if he sees the back
door open, he walks in,
and he then encounters
somebody, and he goes,
"Oh, hello Mr. Spencer."
- Bert Spencer: Yeah, that's
the theory of yours, is it?
- David Wilson: No, it's
actually--a theory that's
in a lot--
- Bert Spencer:
It's a police theory.
Do you believe the police?
The lies they've
talked about me.
And you still believe them.
- David Wilson: I
think that he was shot,
Carl was shot because he could
identify the person or killer--
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: Who
was breaking in.
- Bert Spencer: That's feasible.
- David Wilson:
Is that feasible?
- Bert: It's feasible, I
can't argue against that,
but who were the people?
It certainly wasn't me.
The four who were arrested for
it, I believed had done it.
I don't know, I
believed they did it.
- David Wilson: Do you
still believe they did it?
- Bert Spencer: Yes, I do.
Yes, I do.
So, I don't give a damn what
they protested and how many
rooftops they sat on.
It didn't affect me or
my judgement of them.
I believed they and their group
were deliberately trying to find
a scapegoat and I fit it.
That's what I believe.
I won't change.
If that upsets you, tough.
- David Wilson: The evidence
against them was thrown
out eventually.
- Bert Spencer: Yes, yeah.
- David Wilson: So--
- Bert Spencer: The same damn cops that caused
that handled my case.
They might throw mine out.
Why not?
♪ music playing ♪
- James D'Arcy: The Bridgewater Four would find themselves
at the heart of one
of the greatest miscarriages
of justice in British
legal history.
Their convictions were
eventually quashed when it
was proven the detectives
had faked a confession.
11 years after Carl's murder,
the West Midland serious crime
squad was disbanded following
accusations of abuses of power.
Their mishandling of the case
meant that other leads that
might have been investigated
were never properly followed up.
This included the identity of a
suspect in a photo fit picture
who had been seen near Yew
Tree Farm on the day that Carl
Bridgewater was murdered.
- David Wilson: Here is
the photo fit of one of
the men that was seen that day.
Yeah, and above
is Hubert Wilkes.
- Bert: It should be
more squint, more jawing.
It doesn't look like him.
- David Wilson: You don't
think that looks like him?
- Bert Spencer: No, no.
He had no hair like that,
and he had squinty eyes.
He was jawly.
You know what I mean by that.
- David Wilson: But
that looks uncanny.
You don't think he could've
been at Yew Tree Farm back then?
- Bert Spencer: I
never thought that.
- David Wilson: Is
that a possibility?
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
He lived there.
He got right to be here.
He rented the farm.
- David Wilson: He was
a father figure to you.
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: He's
someone you talk to a lot.
He's someone that you discuss
these things with a lot.
Did he never mention
the murder at the farm?
- Bert Spencer: No, no.
I didn't know he was
also a main suspect.
I didn't know.
I didn't know that someone
had seen someone they believed
was his vehicle.
Not just a Land Rover,
someone believed it was his,
someone local.
- James D'Arcy: Local
farmworker, Ian Charles,
was working in the fields
next to Yew Tree Farm on
the day Carl was murdered.
In his statement to police, he
reported that he saw what he
thought was Hubert Wilkes'
Land Rover parked in
the driveway
of Yew Tree Farm.
- Ian Charles: "At the
time I saw the Land Rover,
I thought that Mr. Wilkes or
one of his sons or laborers was
visiting the farm."
- James D'Arcy:
Wilkes had already been
questioned by police.
Telling them he had driven his
green BMW to market on that day,
but the day after the farmworker
had spoken to the police,
Wilkes changed a number of
things in his testimony.
Including that he had actually
been driving his Land Rover
on that day.
A persistent rumor was that Bert
killed Wilkes because the farmer
had seen him at Yew Tree Farm,
then taunted him about his
alleged involvement
in Carl's death.
Bert has always denied this,
but a letter found amongst Anne
Wheelan's papers states that
Carl's death was indeed being
discussed the night
Wilkes was shot dead.
- "We can confirm that Mrs.
Spencer told our reporter,
Mr. Tony Bishop, that there
had been talk about the Carl
Bridgewater case at Holloway
House Farm on the evening that
Mr. Wilkes was shot."
- James D'Arcy:
But in the end,
she was satisfied that her
husband has no involvement in
the Carl Bridgewater affair.
- David Wilson: Did Hubert
Wilkes ever mention robberies?
- Bert Spencer: No.
- David Wilson: Did he never
say to you in your house,
"You can do a robbery and
escape through the woods?"
- Bert Spencer: Oh, no!
Don't be silly.
You're being silly, David.
No.
- David Wilson: I got that
directly from your daughter.
- Bert Spencer's daughter:
I never liked him.
When he came to our house,
I particularly remember
he would stand at
the fire with his back
to the fire
and I was lying in the sitting.
He would just constantly talk
about robberies and how you
could commit the perfect crime
by escaping through the woods.
And I'd lie there and
think, "Oh, just shut up!"
Because I never
particularly liked the man.
I never felt any
liking towards him.
- James D'Arcy: Holloway House
Farm is the final stop of the
day, Bert's life changed forever
when he murdered Hubert Wilkes.
In the minds of some, it was
events surrounding that murder
that still inextricably
link him to the death
of Carl Bridgewater.
- David Wilson: Farmer Wilkes
farmed Yew Tree Farm as well.
- Bert Spencer: And this farm,
that's Holloway
House Farm there.
This is as it was.
- David Wilson: Oh my gosh,
it looks pretty impressive,
doesn't it?
- Bert Spencer: That is how it
was, and I was his gardener,
his chauffeur--
- David Wilson: Bert,
you wanted to say something
to Carl Bridgewater
at Yew Tree Farm.
What would you say
to Hubert Wilkes?
- Bert Spencer: I am so
ashamed, I'll say nothing.
- David Wilson: Nothing?
- Bert Spencer: No, this hurts.
This hurts because I
shot him, didn't I?
A friend.
It hurts, it hurts me.
I don't expect you to
understand that it does.
- David Wilson: No,
I understand it.
I understand that it's very
emotional and overpowering.
- Bert Spencer: As much as
I went bloody mad, didn't I?
For a few minutes.
- David Wilson: And again,
some of the things that
I would want to ask of you,
how come Hubert Wilkes ends up
dead in exactly the same
way asCarl Bridgewater?
- Bert Spencer: I
don't know about that.
I don't know the circumstances,
or what do you call it?
Coincidence or whatever.
But apparently, it did.
- David Wilson: Yeah,
that must strike you.
That coincidence must
strike you as eerie and odd.
- Bert Spencer: Yes, yes.
They said to me--the
police said to me,
it's exactly the
way as Carl died.
Exactly the same.
- James D'Arcy: Next time
on Interview with a Murderer,
Bert stuns professor Wilson by
calling in on his secretary
and cast iron alibi, Barbara.
- Bert Spencer:
Barbara lived up here.
- James D'Arcy:
But after 36 years,
can she still back up his
story that he was at work
all day when Carl was shot?
- David Wilson: Can you
remember if Bert took lunch
that day that Carl
Bridgewater was murdered?
- James D'Arcy: And breaking
nearly a four decade long
silence, a crucial new
witness comes forward.
- David Wilson: Somebody
has made contact with us,
that I've been wanting
to speak to throughout
this entire process.
Bert's first wife, Janette has
never spoken before on camera.
I don't know what
she's going to say,
but I know that whatever
she says is going to
be absolutely fascinating.
- David Wilson: What does
it mean to be labeled as a
murderer?
- Bert Spencer:
Just stop a minute.
- James D'Arcy: Could
farmer Hubert Wilkes,
who Bert murdered, have been a
witness at Yew Tree Farm the day
Carl died?
- David Wilson: You don't think
he could've been at Yew Tree
Farm that day?
Is that a possibility?
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- James D'Arcy: And professor
Wilson fears that Bert may be
displaying some worrying
personality traits.
- David Wilson: Am I
dealing with somebody who is
psychopathic?
- James D'Arcy: For all
the suspicions about Bert,
there has always been one person
who has supported his claim that
he had nothing to do
with the murder of Carl.
His secretary and cast
iron alibi, Barbara.
Barbara has refused all
requests for interviews in the
intervening years, but Bert has
returned to Staffordshire with
criminologist David Wilson, in
a bid to once and for all prove
that he had nothing to
do with Carl's death.
During the trip, Bert stuns
everyone by asking the car to
stop outside Barbara's home.
- Bert Spencer:
Barbara lived up here.
Oh, we got a camera!
Hello, camera.
Oh, I got the wrong place,
does Barbara live here?
- Julie; Who wants to know?
- Bert Spencer: Are you Julie?
I'm Bert.
Come here!
Come here, [INDISCERNIBLE]
- Julie: Oh my God!
- Bert Spencer: All those years.
You look lovely.
Is she in?
Is she alright?
Barbara!
- Barbara: Bert!
- Bert Spencer: Hey, babe.
Look at you.
- Barbara: I'm going to cry.
- Bert Spencer:
Let's cry together.
Come here.
- Barbara: We're not going
through all this again, are we?
- Bert Spencer: No, no.
It's better this time, lovey.
Better this time.
I wrote a book, Barbara.
- Barbara: Yeah.
- Bert Spencer: To show why a
lot of people were wrong in the
allegations.
I'm bloody crying.
And because of the
book--come here, you.
- David Wilson: What's
it like seeing him again?
- Barbara: I can't believe it.
- Bert Spencer: It's
a long, long time.
You still look lovely.
Jump on it, my life.
- David Wilson: Answer me this
question and I want Bert not to
interrupt.
- Bert Spencer: Get on with it.
- David Wilson: Why?
The one thing that has always
confused me about the Colbert
Hospital part of the story
are the records disappearing.
Why do you think
they disappeared?
- Barbara: Well, you see--it was
an open plan and very peculiar
people went there at night.
Didn't they?
- Bert Spencer: They used to
steal computers and tele file in
the carpets.
Sorry, to interfere.
- David Wilson: I never knew I
was going to get a chance to say
hello to you and the one bit
from your witness statements is,
I wonder if we can clarify, is
that you didn't know if perhaps
Bert had gone for lunch on the
day that Carl Bridgewater had
been murdered.
You didn't know--he could
have gone for lunch, you said,
and he normally takes his lunch
between 12:30, could go on,
perhaps as late as, 2.
Can you remember if Bert
took lunch that day that Carl
Bridgewater was murdered?
- Barbara: That's
[INDISCERNIBLE] going back a few
years, I cannot remember what
exactly I said with time,
but this is--I always
used to go from 1-1:30.
At various times, he's be--you
got lots of hospitals to count
with.
You can't count just
with just Colbert.
- David Wilson: So, he could
have gone for lunch on that day
between those times.
- Barbara: Yes.
- David Wilson: Yes.
Well, that's great!
That's what you said in your
statement and I just wanted to
clarify that and
that's wonderful.
Thank you.
You provide Bert with an
alibi because you say, "No,
he was at Colbert Hospital,"
and then there's this bit in the
statement that you make, and
you say, "Well, I take my lunch,
and he could have also taken
his lunch and therefore,
I didn't see him.
It may have been an
open-plan office,
but I didn't see him
continuously during the day,
and he would have disappeared to
go for lunch." - Barbara: Yeah.
- David Wilson: And that's
a possibility, isn't it?
So.
That's the bit of a story that
I'm trying to make sense of.
- Bert Spencer: I might
or I might--I don't know.
I might or might not
have gone for lunch.
I'm just going up for
dinner upstairs, again,
to eat sometimes, but it doesn't
matter because Carl was killed
around 4 something and after
someone saw a blue Viva go into
the farm drive, a quarter
of an hour afterwards,
there were other vehicles who
didn't see the blue Vauxhall
Viva.
So, it had gone in and gone out.
Long before Carl was killed.
- David Wilson: I wonder if it
became so frightening for you,
Bert.
- Bert Spencer: I'm not
frightened of anything;
you should know that.
- David Wilson: I wonder if it
became so frightening for you,
that if you admitted it was
you going for your lunch,
and you turned around
because then people would go,
"Wait a minute," they've already
had the fact that you collected
antiques and "I went for my
lunch and turned my car."
- Bert Spencer: Let me come in.
I could've said if I were there.
I was there, I had
every right to be there.
Anytime, day or night.
I worked down the fields.
I knew the people.
I worked for the farmer
who had the place.
I had a right to be there, but
it wasn't my car on that day.
- David Wilson: That part of
the story, the Vauxhall Viva,
connects you.
Whether you like it
or not, to this story.
- Bert Spencer: Right.
Now, whether you like
it or not, David,
if I had gone home
for lunch on that day,
I did not pass Yew Tree Farm.
- David Wilson: So, did you
go for lunch on that day?
- Bert Spencer: I don't
know, for Christ's sake.
- David Wilson: You don't know!
You have--this is, this is
the story that you've been the
scapegoat for murder, and you
can't remember if you went home
for lunch on that day.
- Bert Spencer: No, I didn't.
- Barbara: He didn't
have a set pattern.
- Bert Spencer: I didn't
have a set pattern, David.
I was all over the bloody place
and my phones never stopped,
and I was up to--
- David Wilson: So,
if you had no set pattern, Bert,
you could've been there at 4
o'clock, you could have
been there at 5 o'clock.
By ruling--by opening up
for other possibilities,
you make it more complicated
and more possible.
- Bert Spencer: Let's
close those possibilities.
Let's close those possibilities
that you're making in your mind.
- David Wilson: I'm not
making them in my mind.
- Bert Spencer: Will you listen?
- David Wilson: Sure.
- Bert Spencer: I didn't
go home for lunch.
You'll have to believe
me; you can't disprove it.
- David Wilson: I don't want
us to argue any further.
- Bert Spencer:
We're not arguing,
we're seeing as discussing
something that touches my
emotions.
I've clarified that.
- David Wilson: Good, I
am pleased about that.
I am pleased that you've
got good memories,
and I'm delighted to
have met you, Barbara.
(music playing)
- James D'Arcy: Bert's claim
that Barbara represents a cast
iron alibi no longer stands up.
(music playing)
Following the astonishing
revelation by Barbara,
David Wilson, reassembles
his team of researchers.
He feels he is not ready to
present his theory about the
involvement Bert may
have had in Carl's death.
- David Wilson: One of the
things that confuses about
Bert's relationship to the
murder at Yew Tree Farm and Carl
Bridgewater has always been that
he had an alibi supported by
Barbara.
Bert says he was at Colbert
Hospital all day on the day that
Carl is murdered and then, of
course, I've been with her,
with Bert Spencer, almost
four decades later,
and I've listened to what
she's had to say and frankly,
what she has to say is that he
has no alibi on that particular
day at all.
We have to put him
under pressure,
either to admit he knows
something more about Yew Tree
Farm.
That he was there earlier
in the day at Yew Tree Farm,
or we have to start saying that
the reason he won't admit to
that is because there is
something even greater that he's
going to have to admit to which
was that he probably was the
killer of Carl Bridgewater.
- James D'Arcy: Professor David
Wilson has spent the last six
months looking into the
murder of newspaper boy Carl
Bridgewater.
This is the fourth and final
meeting between the two men.
- Bert Spencer: You'll be
tormenting somebody else
tomorrow.
- David Wilson: Come in.
- Bert Spencer: Are all
your people as blunt as me?
- James D'Arcy: Professor Wilson
is about to present Bert with
his final findings and offer
his own evaluation of Bert's
psychological state.
- David Wilson: Bring
your Coke if you want.
- Bert Spencer: I will do.
Thank you, very much.
Come on, then.
- David Wilson: Are you alright?
Comfortable?
- Bert Spencer: Yes.
- David Wilson: I think
the phrase that you used,
that I always remember was that
you said to me that you wouldn't
run, and you wouldn't hide.
- Bert Spencer: I never do.
- David Wilson: Your alibi
is that you were at Colbert
Hospital all day on the day that
Carl Bridgewater was murdered.
There was another person at
Colbert Hospital that day,
who of course was, Barbara.
- Bert Spencer: What
about the others?
- David Wilson: Barbara in
particular--
- Bert Spencer: She made a written statement, I believe.
- David Wilson: She made
several written statements.
- Bert Spencer: Okay.
I didn't know that.
Others who worked in the same
floor space, made verbal--"Yes.
Okay, he was here," but
they didn't write it down,
they didn't have to.
The cops at the time didn't do
everything right--what I think
is right.
They didn't ask, "Will
you make a statement,
will you make a statement?"
They didn't feel the need,
someone has already done it.
- David Wilson: And Barbara
made those statements.
- Bert Spencer: Yes, yeah.
- David Wilson: And as you
know, I've tracked down those
statements, and you were
there when I asked her,
could she say that she was there
all afternoon and was able to
verify that you were
there all afternoon.
And she can't.
She can't guarantee what times
you may have left Colbert
Hospital all afternoon.
Means that you don't
have cast iron alibi.
- Bert Spencer: That's fair.
- David Wilson: That alibi
is--well, it disappears, Bert.
- Bert Spencer: I
accept what you say.
I don't have a cast iron alibi.
Do you have any evidence that
I killed Carl Bridgewater?
If you do, Sir,
bring it forward.
If you don't, shut your mouth.
Okay?
You've now annoyed me.
- David Wilson: You get
annoyed by me fairly regularly;
Bert and you threaten
me quite a lot.
- Bert Spencer: That's
not threatening,
it's me talking straight.
- David Wilson: I
also asked you, Bert,
in relation to the
Wilkes' connection.
What was happening the night
that you took Hubert Wilkes'
life?
Your wife at the time made
statements to various places
saying that Carl Bridgewater
was mentioned that night.
- Bert Spencer: Well, if it was,
I wasn't in the room at that
time.
I didn't mention it.
- David Wilson: She says it
was mentioned at the time.
- Bert Spencer: I don't
care what she says,
I'm not rubbishing
her statement.
I'm saying to you, I wasn't in
the room when it was--if it was.
You can't just say, "But she
says it was." That's what I'm
saying to you,
that's my response.
- David Wilson: Hubert
Wilkes was going to you,
I wonder if that plays a part in
relation to what happened at-- -
Bert Spencer: You've just taken
one statement off one person and
that's your God, your law.
My first wife fires venom at me.
Okay?
For four years, after
I was convicted,
it was all lovey-dovey
love letters.
She was visiting, while in
my scrubs until suddenly,
she found another man, and
she came out with this crap.
- David Wilson: Bert--
- Bert Spencer: It is rubbish.
- David Wilson: Did you and
Hubert Wilkes ever discuss
robberies?
- Bert Spencer: We never did.
- David Wilson: Right.
Okay.
Now, I'm going to play you
something, Bert, at the moment.
I particularly wanted you to
hear what your daughter said in
relation to Hubert Wilkes and
the discussion of robberies.
- Bert Spencer's Daughter: "I
particularly remember he would
stand at the fire with
his back to the fire,
and I was lying in
the [INDISCERNIBLE].
He would just constantly
talk about robberies.
And how you could commit the
perfect crime by escaping
through the woods, and I--"
- Bert Spencer: I'm sorry,
I don't agree with that.
Hubert Wilkes used to come to
my house and drink whiskey.
Never discussed
robberies with me.
- David Wilson: So,
your daughter is wrong.
- Bert Spencer:
She's made a mistake.
- David Wilson: Well, she
doesn't think that, Bert.
- Bert Spencer: Okay, a lot
of people think I killed Carl
Bridgewater.
I know I didn't, but I
can't change their opinion.
- David Wilson: This is really
where I'm coming to you.
Would you mind if I
showed you something?
- Bert Spencer: Show me.
- David Wilson: These
are distressing.
- Bert Spencer:
[INDISCERNIBLE] mind, show me.
- David Wilson: These are
distressing photographs.
- Bert Spencer: Show me.
- David Wilson: These are the
crime scene photographs of Carl
Bridgewater.
- Bert Spencer: Alright.
That's at the scene, I assume.
- David Wilson: Yeah.
- Bert Spencer: Yes, okay.
- David Wilson: I've shown you
that because I think with the
fact that you no
longer have an alibi,
that something happened that day
that involved you at Yew Tree
Farm and I want you
to listen again.
- Bert Spencer Daughter:
"I've always felt that he saw
something that day
that killed him inside.
If a story ever came out
like, "I finished my shift,
and I've got a little bit
of time and I thought,
I'll go and do that errand," and
then suddenly hear a gunshot go
off, and then, after it's
all dispersed--and you see
something."
- Bert Spencer: Tell, how come--
- Bert Spencer's
Daughter: "On what you're
witnessing and
what you're seeing,
and you're just horrified.
I have tried to discuss that
with him on an occasion,
but he was very emotional."
- David Wilson:
Was that what happened?
- Bert Spencer: No.
- David Wilson: Did you go
to Yew Tree Farm that day?
Your daughter thinks that
you did go to Yew Tree Farm.
- Bert Spencer: Yes, I
just heard what you said,
she also thinks it
was after my shift.
After 5:00 PM.
Too late.
Too late, mate.
Even if I got there a
quarter past, 20 past.
There's no gunshot,
that was an hour ago.
- David Wilson: Did you
go after your shift?
- Bert Spencer: No, I did not.
- David Wilson: You've
forgotten the time, she said.
- David Wilson: Did you
go after your shift?
- Bert Spencer: No,
for Christ's sake.
What for?
What?
I wasn't working
there that month.
What for?
- David Wilson: Well,
after our first interview,
I did a P Scan on you.
- Bert Spencer: What's that?
- David Wilson: It
means, psychopathy scan.
So, this isn't a
clinical diagnosis,
this is a way that I can gain
some insight into the person
that I'm talking to and the
total score for you was in the
high range.
A total score that falls in the
high range should be course for
serious concern.
It suggests that the person of
interest may have many or most
of the features that
define psychopathy.
Such a person is likely
to be egocentric, callous,
cold-blooded, predatory,
impulsive, irresponsible,
dominant, deceptive,
manipulative and lacking in
empathy, guild or genuine
remorse for socially deviant and
criminal acts.
And that fits you to a T.
- Bert Spencer: It also
fits you, you bugger,
some of the things you've said.
To a T.
- David Wilson:
This is you, Bert.
- Bert Spencer: So, you've
just condemned me, haven't you?
- David Wilson: You are somebody
that I regard-- - Bert Spencer:
As a psychopath.
- David Wilson: As a liar, as
somebody who has bent the truth.
As somebody who is
manipulative, as coning.
You are not this kindly
old grandfather figure,
that is your shtick, Bert, and I
see through it and all I can say
to you is, in the absence
of you having any alibi,
because you were there when
Barbara says she cannot stand up
where you were on the afternoon
that Carl Bridgewater was
murdered.
- Bert Spencer: I have
an answer for you.
- David Wilson: I am going to
be taking this material to the
police.
- Bert Spencer: Yeah.
- David Wilson: Because I think
this case needs to be reopened.
- Bert Spencer: Right,
I'm not going to say,
"Let me get a word in," I am
going to get a word in, David.
I think you need to
see a psychiatrist.
You are wrong.
So very wrong, your
egoistic, all Mr. Important,
what the hell does it
matter what you think?
The evidence shows how the hell
can I be there when I wasn't
there?
You'd like to prove that?
Go ahead, go what you want, but
I think you need psychiatric
treatment, son.
There's something wrong
with the way that you think.
That is my belief.
- David Wilson: I think now,
it's really a question for other
people to make a decision
on these kinds of things.
- Bert Spencer: Let them do it.
- David Wilson: All I can
do is tell you what I felt,
and I will raise this elsewhere.
- Bert Spencer: Okay, do that.
- David Wilson: Thank you.
- Bert Spencer: Big
silence in the room,
he's a fucking nut case.
I didn't know that,
I didn't know that.
- David Wilson: He knows that if
he starts admitting that he was
at Yew Tree Farm, then actually,
then the police have got to be
re-interviewing him.
- Bert Spencer: It's all a
load of absolute nonsense,
it really is.
- Christine: I could not
believe what I was hearing.
- Bert Spencer: He can't work
it out, so instead of filling,
he wasn't me as a scapegoat.
- Christine: I'll
certainly stand by my man.
Every inch of the way.
- Bert Spencer: This
psychopath needs a cuddle.
- David Wilson: I personally
still think with the fact that
Barbara can no longer
stand up his alibi,
this case should be reopened.
- Bert Spencer: Alright.
(music playing)
- David Wilson: As ever in
the world of Bert Spencer,
just when you think you've
got some kind of conclusion,
other possibilities immediately
offer themselves up.
Somebody has made
contact with us,
that I've been
wanting to speak to,
throughout this entire process.
Bert's first wife, Janet has
never spoken before on camera
and has maintained a
silence for some 38 years.
I don't know what
she's going to say,
but I know that whatever she
says is going to be absolutely
fascinating.
Janet, how long were you
married to Bert Spencer for?
- Janet: About 16-17 years.
- David Wilson: Was he
popular with the girls?
- Janet: Yes, yes.
With everyone, he
was very well-loved.
- David Wilson: When you got to
really know him for all those
years, was there another
side to him, as well?
- Janet: Oh, yes.
Yes.
- David Wilson: Describe
that other side for me.
- Janet: Dark.
He could be very
volatile at times,
if things upset
him or--you know,
he had a bit too much to drink,
he could change drastically.
- David Wilson: Was
he ever nasty to you?
- Janet: Oh, yes.
Yeah.
- David Wilson: In what way?
- Janet: Oh, well,
many--he's hit me.
He hit me on a few occasions,
but it was just very frightening
and menacing when
he lost his temper.
He could be very intimidating.
- David Wilson: Did
he intimidate you?
- Janet: Yes, yeah.
- David Wilson: It sounds as if
your marriage was like walking
on eggshells.
- Janet: A lot of
the time, yeah.
(music playing)
- James D'Arcy: Janet was
present the night that farmer,
Hubert Wilkes, was killed.
The murder has been described as
a carbon copy of the killing of
Carl Bridgewater, but what
really happened that night and
did it have anything to do
with the murder of Carl?
- David Wilson: Can I take you
back to the night that Hubert
Wilkes was murdered?
Can you describe to
me what happened?
- Janet: When out to the farm,
I went into the house with Bert,
went into the dining room where
I used to carry out some--where
the payroll [INDISCERNIBLE], and
then eventually when I finished
the work that I had to do.
I joined them in the lounge and
my first reaction when I saw
Bert was that he seemed to have
quite a lot to drink in the
actual time.
Jane had mentioned a book
that she had been reading,
and it sounded interesting, so
she went upstairs to fetch the
book for me.
And then immediately,
she'd done that,
Bert said that he was
going to go to the toilet.
So, off he toddles, and I'm
sitting with Mr. Wilkes in the
sitting, and he seemed to
have been gone for some time,
and I was getting
concerned, if he was okay.
And after that, Bert appeared,
I said, "Oh, there you are,
" and then he sort of slopped
in and then turned around fully,
and I could see that he
could get a gun in his hand,
and then he just
shot Mr. Wilkes.
Severed the head, while he
was sitting in the sitting.
- David Wilson: What
did he do to you?
- Janet: Well, immediately after
that had happened, I thought,
"I'm next," and in the split
second that he--he hadn't turned
the gun on me.
I ran out of there and grabbed
a gun with two hands and shouted
at him, "Do you realize
what you've done?"
But at that point, Jane came
into the far door again,
took one look, screamed and ran.
So, he took off after Jane.
So, I ran into the kitchen,
tried to unlock the door and I
couldn't unlock the door.
And it was in darkness and I ran
and hid under the kitchen table,
and I [INDISCERNIBLE], I could
hear the gun clatter on the
floor, and I thought, "He is
going to hear that."
He came running in again, and he
ran out into the yard.
- Bert Spencer: "Janet!"
- Janet: I went through the
bottom door into the hallway,
picked up the phone, and he
appeared from the other door
down the hall with another gun.
A complete gun, not a cut-off
one and he had proceeded to hit
me in the head with it, time
after time, until I went down,
and I was thinking, "Now, this
is it." And then Jane came in
again, through the door, in
the hallway and screamed,
and he ran after her again.
So, [INDISCERNIBLE],
I've never been out,
but [INDISCERNIBLE] saved me,
and--after that it was just a
question of trying to escape
the farm without him finding me.
- David Wilson: And you've
got absolutely no doubt he was
trying to kill you.
- Janet: Well...he
didn't shoot me.
I can't understand why
he didn't--a few more,
he probably would've killed me.
A few more hits across the head.
- David Wilson: On the night
in question in December,
had there been discussion about
the Bridgewater case and the
appeal being lodged by
the Bridgewater Four?
- Janet: Well, because I was
in the--office for most of the
time, I can't--I can't say.
I mean, it has been
mentioned since.
I'm not sure--we did see
something on the television once
together, Bert and I, that they
were appealing against their
conviction.
I'm not sure if it was
that night, but he did say,
"If they get off, they'll be
after me." - David Wilson: Did
he ever explain to you
why he shot Hubert Wilkes?
- Janet: No, never.
Never--he said he
had a black-out.
He never gave any
logical explanation.
No.
- David Wilson: Bert claims that
Mr. Wilkes was going to give you
a special cocktail.
So as to be able to
have sex with you.
Is there any truth in that?
Was that ever mentioned to you?
- Janet: No.
I know he's given that as a
reason because he's pretty down
and writing to me, in the
following years, but no.
I didn't know anything.
If he had arranged something, I
didn't know anything about it.
I don't believe it anyway.
I just don't believe it.
- David Wilson: Did you discuss
the Bridgewater case with Bert?
I mean, here's the
bit that confuses me.
I went back to Ascot Gardens
where you used to live and the
Bridgewater's lived
a few doors up.
- Janet: That's right.
- David Wilson: Did
you socialize with the
Bridgewater's?
- Janet: We didn't actually
socialize with them,
but I know on one occasion
when we had a partner,
they came and had a drink.
You know, at the house,
except for loads of people,
there were quite a
few, actually, but yes,
they did come out.
So, we knew them because
they were our neighbors,
we knew the son.
- David Wilson: Carl.
- Janet: Yeah, so, I can't
understand why he says he
doesn't know them because I did.
- David Wilson: Janet, can
you describe what you remember
happening on the day that Carl
was murdered when you went home?
- Janet: I came into the house
and I saw Bert standing there
and--with his hands in his
pockets, bloody language,
telling me that he
wasn't very happy.
And I also noticed a jumper
had been pegged on the line,
which--which a man had put up
because women don't peg jumpers
on like that.
- David Wilson: Was that
one of Bert's work jumpers?
What color was it?
- Janet: No, it was
a casual jumper.
Green.
Green--jumper.
- David Wilson: Did you
ever see that jumper again?
- Janet: No, never.
- David Wilson: But was it clear
to you that Bert had washed the
jumper?
- Janet: Oh yeah.
- David Wilson: It
just disappeared.
- Janet: Just disappeared.
He went to bed, which he did.
He went to bed early and I
then watched the news on the
television.
And as I watched it
and--everything about it,
you know, the fact who he
was, where he lived, the boy,
and what had happened to him.
[INDISCERNIBLE],
couldn't believe it.
Washed, you know,
washed all over.
I went upstairs and
shook his shoulder,
he wasn't asleep and
said to him, "Please God,
please tell me you didn't have
anything to do with that." And
he said, "No, I didn't, but
don't you think they'd be after
me, if it was my patch," or
words to that effect."
That's what he said.
- David Wilson: And that
must have been quite odd.
How would he know about it?
- Janet: Well, I've
wondered since, actually,
but I can't assure that nothing
was on the news earlier,
but I can't say how--how
he could've--I don't know.
- David Wilson: But he wasn't
watching the news with you.
- Janet: No, no.
He'd gone to bed.
- David Wilson: So,
you go upstairs.
He's still awake, and you
ask him, "Please, God,
tell me you had nothing to
do with that." And he knew
immediately what you
were talking about.
- Janet: Oh yeah, he did.
- David Wilson:
Was Bert worried?
- Janet: He was--he was
concerned, and I said,
"I don't know why
you're worried,
because you were at work." -
David Wilson: And what did he
say to that?
- Janet: He says, "I wasn't
there all day." - David Wilson:
He said he wasn't
at work all day.
- Janet: He said, "I wasn't
there all the time because--" I
said, "Well?"
He says, "Because I didn't
feel well." So, he says,
"I was in the toilet
for a long time.
A stomach problem.
'' I said, "Surely,
someone must have seen you.
Somebody must have heard you
or said you were going to the
toilet to sit now."
And he says, "Well,
the only one that could probably
say something is Barbara up the
road." She lived a few
doors away, Barbara.
So, he went and fetched her.
- David Wilson: He
went and fetched her.
- Janet: To come
down to the house.
She said, "Yes, of
course," you know,
"I can give a statement
to the police.
Don't worry." - David Wilson:
Did you believe that statement?
- Janet: Well, knowing what he
had said to me, I just thought,
she was probably
helping him out,
but it wasn't really that
important because he wasn't the
culprit, or I was
hoping he wasn't.
- David Wilson: Bert
clearly collected antiques,
bought and sold antiques.
Were you ever worried that some
of those antiques were stolen?
- Janet: No, I never
suspected that at all.
We did a lot of
wheeling and dealing,
but a friend told me that a bag
that contained antiques had been
found in their shed because
someone had seen Bert coming out
of their driveway.
And so, the husband went down
to have a look in the shed and
found this bag of antiques,
brassware and copper.
So, following on what
my friend had told me,
when I went to visit
Bert in prison,
I did question him
about this bag.
And his words to me were, "You
must never ever tell anybody
about that.
Ever."
So, I said, "Well,
okay, but you know,
what happened to them?"
He said that he buried them
somewhere around the Crestwood
area which is off the A449.
- David Wilson: So, the
implication was that he had
stolen those antiques, tried to
hide them in the shed of one of
his friends and then when he
was caught having done so,
challenged by your friend, he
then buried the antique that he
had stolen.
Where do those antiques
that were buried came from?
Do you think they could have
come from Yew Tree Farm?
- Janet: Well, that's got to be
the thinking of all of us as the
friend asked him to move them,
and it was close to the Carl
Bridgewater time.
I can only assume that he's got
something that he shouldn't have
had.
- David Wilson: Janet,
in September 1978,
did Bert own a shotgun?
- Janet: Yes, he did.
- David Wilson: What
happened to that shotgun?
- Janet: I remember him saying,
probably the day after Carl
Bridgewater--that Carl
Bridgewater murder, he ought to,
you know, get rid of it.
So, take it somewhere.
And I don't know
what happened to it,
but there was a gun in
the house at the time.
And he did have a
shotgun license for it.
- David Wilson: And he
disposed of the shotgun,
the day after Carl Bridgewater--
- Janet: Got shot, yeah.
- David Wilson: When you put
all the various pieces of
information that you're in
possession of together now,
what does it lead
you to conclude?
- Janet: It's not
concrete evidence,
but I really believe that
if he didn't actually shoot,
he knows more about
that than he's let on.
- David Wilson: Would it
surprise you if the truth was,
Bert Spencer, your ex-husband
killed Carl Bridgewater?
Would that surprise you?
- Janet: No, it wouldn't.
- David Wilson: In fact, do you
suspect that's what happened?
- Janet: Well, you know, it's
hard to say, but deep down, yes.
I probably--I do really, now.
(music playing)
- James D'Arcy: Following
Janet's damning claims,
Bert is given a right
to reply to them.
- Producer: On the
day of Carl's murder,
Janet says she returned home to
find a green jumper hanging on
the clothesline.
She believes Bert hung it
there, she says he was behaving
strangely.
She says she never
saw that jersey again.
- Bert Spencer: Neither did I.
I have no idea what that means,
if you'd like to expand upon
that.
I was in uniform, don't
forget--if I was there.
Green jumper?
Sorry.
- Producer: After returning
from a family celebration,
Janet saw the news report
about Carl's murder on the TV,
she rushed to tell
Bert who was in bed,
saying Carl had been killed at
Yew Tree Farm, and she said,
"Please God, please tell me
you had nothing to do with it,
" to which Bert
replied, "No, I didn't,
but don't you think
they'll be after me?"
- Bert Spencer: Oh,
that's nonsense.
I did not say that I
don't agree with that.
- Producer: Janet said Bert
added the following explanation.
"It happened on my patch." She
never understood why he made
that remark but realizes
now how odd it is.
- Bert Spencer: I would never
have made that remark and don't
accept it.
- Producer: According to Janet,
Bert initially told her that he
didn't have a proper alibi at
work because he had been in the
toilet most of the afternoon,
due to a bad tummy.
She said, later, he physically
fetched Barbara from up the
road, in order to
give him an alibi.
- Bert Spencer: What
absolute nonsense.
Read the police
statements from Barbara.
- Producer: Janet said that
Bert had a shotgun and a shotgun
license but disposed of the
shotgun the day after Carl
Bridgewater was killed.
- Bert Spencer: No, I disposed
of the shotgun--I used to buy
and sell shotguns.
I had a shotgun license, I
disposed of it about two months
before Carl was killed and the
police are fully aware of that,
they found the gun.
- Producer: Bert once stored
some antiques, copper and brass,
in a friend's shed and was
spotted in the shed removing
them.
He was asked to move
them which he did,
this happens after Carl's death,
but before the death of Hubert
Wilkes.
When Janet later asked
Bert about this in prison,
he told her that they
were buried near the A449
[INDISCERNIBLE] Road, and she
was never to tell anybody about
that, ever.
- Bert Spencer: I do not
agree with that comment,
it is nonsense.
- Producer: Janet finally
says, after many years,
she has reached the conclusion
that Bert probably did kill Carl
Bridgewater, though at the time
she didn't want to believe it of
her husband.
- Bert Spencer: I am
aware of her opinion,
like many others in the
world, she is welcome
to her opinion.
It happens I don't
agree with it.
(music playing)
I promise you, if you bring
evidence that can be accepted in
a high court, that what you say
is true, I promise you, Janet,
no harm will come to you.
No threats will be made to
you, but I would--I am ready to
instigate my own kamikaze method
and I promise you; you would be,
I would make sure you
are immediately arrested,
charged and found guilty of
conspiring in the courts of
justice for all these years, of
putting four men behind bars,
unnecessarily, and
more seriously, Janet,
being an accessory
after the fact.
Regardless, of all the
allegations that keep coming my
way, hear this, I will never,
ever be a scapegoat for the
murder of Carl
Bridgewater, by golly,
I've had enough
of this snipping.
I've had enough, Janet,
and when I've had enough,
I may well institute kamikaze.
(music playing)